Finding Aid for Allan M. Williams Papers 1930-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Allan M. Williams Papers 1930-1979
Williams, Allan M. (Allan Mackenzie), 1892-1979.
Engineer-manager of the Ionia County (Mich.) Road Commission. Speeches, articles, correspondence, press releases, newspaper clippings, photographs, and miscellanea relating to his work as county engineer; also contains material concerning the Ionia County Free Fair and the American Road Builders' Association.
85541 Aa 2
6 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The papers were donated by the Allan M. Williams estate (donor no. 6349 ) in 1979.
The collection is open for research.
Allan M. Williams was born, in 1892, and raised in Ludington, Michigan. Graduating from Ludington High School in 1912, he entered Kalamazoo College, and then transferred to the College of Engineering of the University of Michigan after his freshman year. In 1918 Williams joined the Michigan State Highway Department as project engineer, where the following year he drafted the state's first complete highway map. He became engineer-manager of the Ionia County Road Commission in 1919, while continuing to serve as project engineer for the state until 1927. Williams held his position with Ionia County until his retirement in 1957.
As engineer-manager of the Ionia County Road Commission, Williams placed in 1929 the first roadside picnic table - constructed from planks salvaged from old guard rails - in Michigan and perhaps the United States. The table was placed in Boston Township on US 16 and soon proved popular with motorists. It came to the attention of the Michigan State Highway Department, which ordered additional picnic tables from the Ionia County Road Commission to be placed throughout the state. Williams also developed Green View Point. Located on M-21, it was the first trunkline scenic turnout.
In addition to his professional activities, Williams served Ionia County by helping to establish the Ionia County Memorial Hospital. Williams was also active in the Ionia Free Fair Association sitting on the fair board in various capacities from 1938-1964. He was president of the association for twelve terms.
Allan M. Williams, esteemed by members of his profession, was elected president of the Southern Michigan Road Commissioner's Association in 1953. He also served as president of the American Road Builders' Association, county and local roads division in 1955 and 1956. In 1940 Williams won a first place award from Better Roads Magazine for excellence in county road management.
The Allan M. Williams Collection includes much material dealing with Williams' professional interests and concerns. There are papers relating to the American Road Builders' Association and Michigan organizations, including articles and speeches written by Williams. In addition, there are materials relating to his unsuccessful primary campaigns for State Road Commissioner in 1941 and 1943 and for State Senator in 1962. Finally, materials relating to the Ionia County Free Fair are quite rich, including correspondence, financial information, and publicity dealing with far range planning and the day-to-day operations of the Ionia County Free Fair and its governing board.
The collections has been arranged into the following series: Biographical/Personal; Ionia County Free Fair; Speeches and writings; American Road Builders' Association; Other Organizations; Projects and related; Political file; Community projects; Photographs.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan--Ionia County.; American Road Builders' Association.; Elections--Michigan--1962.; Engineers--Michigan--Ionia County.; Fairs--Michigan--Ionia County.; Ionia County (Mich.); Ionia County (Mich.). Board of County Road Commissioners.; Ionia County Free Fair (Mich.); Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Michigan--Politics and government--1922-1928.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan. State Highway Dept.; Roads--Michigan--Ionia County.; Williams, Allan M. (Allan Mackenzie), 1892-1979.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Fairs--Michigan--Ionia County.; Ionia County (Mich.); Ionia County Free Fair (Mich.); Political elections--1962.; Politicians--Michigan--Ionia County.; Road construction.; Williams, Allan M. (Allan Mackenzie), 1892-1979.
Contributors:
Green, Fred W. (Fred Warren), 1872-1936.; Lawrence, Howard Cyrus, 1890-1961.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Biography 1941, 1962, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Congratulatory correspondence concerning anniversaries, articles written, and work accomplished 1944-1962, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Congratulatory correspondence upon occasion of his retirement 1957 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 5 folders (Box 1)
- Ionia County Free Fair
  - Fair history undated, 1946, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Legal papers undated, 1917-1962 (Box 1)
  - Articles of association undated, 1923, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Resolutions undated, 1944 (Box 1)
  - By-laws and minutes undated, 1923 (Box 1)
  - Department heads 1958-1961 (sampled) (Box 1)
  - Financial report 1930 (Box 1)
  - Financial report 1957 (Box 1)
  - Memoranda undated, 1951, 1956, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Howard C. Lawrence 1939-1942, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, responses to governor's day luncheons 1952 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding parade 1954 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding acts for fair entertainment 1961 (Box 1)
  - General correspondence 1945-1967
    - A-I, 11 folders (Box 1)
    - J-Z, 20 folders (Box 2)
  - General correspondence 1958-1964 (Box 2)
  - General correspondence 1965-1971 (Box 2)
  - Schedules and instructions 1952 (Box 2)
  - Schedules 1958-1959, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Synopsis of possible program 1945 (Box 2)
  - Programs 1937-1978 (scattered) (Box 2)
  - Public relations program undated (Box 2)
  - Publicity undated, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Press releases
    - 1943, 1945 (Box 2)
    - 1959-1963, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Grandstand program 1956 (Box 3)
  - Exhibit locations 1957 (Box 3)
  - Livestock and needlework prize winners 1959 (Box 3)
  - Building maintenance undated, 1957-1962 (Box 3)
  - Blueprints and drawings for fair structures undated, 1957, 1959 (Box 3)
  - Article on Allan Williams and the fair 1954 (Box 3)
  - Speech re. classification of county fairs for concession space rules 1957 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings undated, 1930-1979, 14 folders (Box 3)
  - Miscellanea
    - Undated (Box 3)
    - 1959 (Box 3)
    - 1962 (Box 3)
  - AMW resignations from Fair Board 1941, 1963 (Box 3)
- Speeches and writings
  - Miscellaneous
    - Undated (Box 3)
    - 1927-1955 (Box 3)
    - 1956-1963 (Box 3)
  - "Food for Thought Prepared Especially for Scraper Truck Drivers" undated (Box 3)
  - "The Farm to Market Road" 1945 (Box 3)
  - "Highway Sanding-Ionia County Method" 1945 (Box 3)
  - "The Why of the Spring Break-up" 1945 (Box 3)
  - "Outlook? It's encouraging" published in Better Roads, 1946 (Box 3)
  - "Spring Break-up of Roads" 1947 (Box 3)
  - "The National Road Program and Its Impact on Michigan's Highway Situation: A County Viewpoint" 1955 (Box 3)
  - Speech: "County Road Commission Finances" before the Northern Michigan Association of Road Commissioners and Engineers 1935 (Box 3)
  - Speech: "Response before National Highway Conference" 1955 (Box 3)
  - Speech: "Efficient and Economical County Highway Administration" before the Purdue Road Show 1956 (Box 3)
  - Article: "The Public Relations of the Ionia County Road Commission" by Ben Williams 1943 (Box 3)
- American Road Builders' Association
  - Correspondence 1941-1968, 16 folders (Box 3)
  - Press releases 1956-1957, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Newsletter 1962-1963 (Box 4)
  - Statistical and legal information, undated 1941, 1955-1958 (Box 4)
  - Minutes and agendas undated, 1953-1957 (Box 4)
  - Programs of annual meetings 1952-1956 (Box 4)
  - Presentations before National Highway Conference in Gatlinburg, Tennessee 1955, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence regarding National Highway Conference at Mackinac Island 1956 (Box 4)
  - Miscellanea regarding National Highway Conference at Mackinac Island (Box 4)
  - Road Builders' Newsletter, 1953, 1955-1956 (Box 4)
  - Better Roads Magazine Correspondence 1943-1958, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Newspaper clippings undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellanea (Box 4)
- Other Organizations
  - American Society of Civil Engineers meeting notices 1975 (Box 4)
  - Purdue University Highway Extension News 1955-1957 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Engineering Society 1959-1967 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Highway Commission Weekly News 1973 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Roads and Construction tear sheets 1953-1958 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Asphalt Paving Association correspondence and program 1960, 1973 (Box 4)
  - Michigan State Trunkline five year construction program 1957-1962 (Box 4)
  - County Road Association 1959, 1964, 1974-1976 (Box 4)
  - Northern Michigan Road Commissioners' Association
    - Cadillac meeting 1941 (Box 4)
    - Charlevoix meeting 1951 (Box 4)
  - Upper Peninsula Road Builders' Association Ironwood meeting 1941 (Box 4)
  - Association of Southern Michigan Road Commissions, Grand Rapids Convention 1947 (Box 4)
  - Association of Southern Michigan Road Commissions 1978 (Box 4)
  - Ionia County Road Commission
    - Correspondence 1924, 1930, 1945-1953, 1971-1978 (Box 4)
    - Annual report 1938-1952, 14 folders (Box 4)
    - Annual financial report 1954-1955, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Fact sheets and news releases undated, 1945 (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellanea (Box 5)
  - Green Arrow Route Association or M-66 Association
    - Correspondence 1956-1973, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Constitution undated (Box 5)
    - Membership 1960-1962 (Box 5)
    - Minutes and meeting notices 1958-1961 (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings 1958-1959, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Miscellanea (Box 5)
- Projects and related
  - Greenview Point
    - Regrets to invitations to attend dedication 1938 (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings 1973 (Box 5)
  - Louis C. David monument 1930 (Box 5)
  - White's Bridge 1936, 1965, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Ionia County Park undated, 1934, 1940, 1959 (Box 5)
  - Evergreen and Brook Crest trailer courts 1959-1973 (Box 5)
  - Roadside picnic tables
    - Correspondence 1957-1973 (Box 5)
    - "The History of Roadside Development in Michigan," by E.C. Eckert 1956 (Box 5)
    - "Williams Founded State's Roadside Tables" undated (Box 5)
    - Newspaper clippings, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - West Michigan Tourist Association
    - Correspondence 1951-1955, 1963, 1974-1978 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous papers 1954, 1975, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Work diary 1950-1951, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Construction projects
    - Saranac flood span correspondence 1960-1961 (Box 5)
    - Saranac flood span 1960 blueprints (Box 5)
    - Grand River Bridge in Saranac
      - Correspondence 1960-1963 (Box 5)
      - Blueprints undated, 1962 (Box 5)
      - Financial records 1960-1963 (Box 5)
      - Agreement to repair bridge 1962 (Box 5)
      - Miscellanea 1958-1963 (Box 5)
  - Main Street improvements in Westphalia 1961-1963 (Box 5)
  - Dausmoa Dam project 1958, 1974 (Box 5)
- Political file
  - Fred Green campaigns and related
    - Fred Green correspondence 1926-1929 (Box 5)
    - Fred Green gubernatorial campaign newspaper clippings 1926 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous Green campaign material undated (Box 5)
    - Program from presentation of Green portrait 1931 (Box 5)
  - State Highway Commissioner primary campaign 1941
    - Correspondence 1941 (Box 5)
    - Press releases and statements 1941 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous delegate lists undated, 1941 (Box 5)
    - Republican state convention delegate and alternate lists 1941
      - Alcona-Branch (Box 5)
      - Calhoun-Luce (Box 5)
      - Macomb-Wexford (Box 5)
  - State Highway Commissioners Campaign 1941
    - Leroy Smith correspondence (Box 6)
    - Scrapbook 1941 (Box 6)
    - Miscellanea (Box 6)
  - State Highway Commissioners Primary Campaign 1943
    - Correspondence 1943 (Box 6)
    - Delegate lists, Oakland and Wexford Counties 1943 (Box 6)
    - Financial information 1943 (Box 6)
    - Publicity undated (Box 6)
  - State Senate primary 1962
    - Correspondence 1962, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Financial information 1962 (Box 6)
    - Campaign literature 1962 (Box 6)
    - Press releases 1962 (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings 1962 (Box 6)
  - Miscellanea 1950-1956 (Box 6)
- Community projects
  - Ionia County hospital
    - Correspondence 1950, 1955 (Box 6)
    - Program 1963 (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings 1949-1951 (Box 6)
    - Horse show
      - Correspondence 1946 (Box 6)
      - Programs 1946 (Box 6)
      - Instructions 1946 (Box 6)
      - Clippings 1946 (Box 6)
      - Mailing lists and miscellanea 1946 (Box 6)
      - Programs from other shows 1941-1948 (Box 6)
  - Civil Defense
    - Notebook, including reports of scrap collection 1942 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence 1950-1954 (Box 6)
    - Inventory and check list 1953-1955 (Box 6)
    - 4671st Ground Observer Squadron newsletter 1953-1954 (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings 1952-1956 (Box 6)
  - Ionia County Airport
    - Correspondence 1937, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellanea 1937 (Box 6)
    - Clippings 1937, 1955, 1968 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence 1955-1956, 1968 (Box 6)
    - Dedication of airport 1968 (Box 6)
  - Community Chest
    - Correspondence 1953-1954 (Box 6)
    - Financial information 1953 (Box 6)
    - Campaign committee 1953 (Box 6)
    - Donor lists undated (Box 6)
    - Campaign supplies and instructions 1953-1954 (Box 6)
    - Newspaper clippings 1953-1954 (Box 6)
  - Rotary 1969 (Box 6)
  - Chamber of Commerce correspondence 1942-1952 (Box 6)
  - Michigan training unit list of volunteer counselors 1963-1964 (Box 6)
  - Elks 1952 (Box 6)
  - Ionia County Historical Society 1976-1978 (Box 6)
  - Ionia County history 1933, 1973 (Box 6)
  - Phoenix project 1950-1951 (Box 6)
  - Michigan Civil Service Commission 1964 (Box 6)
  - Miscellanea (Box 6)
- Photographs
  - Personal (Box 6)
  - Awards (Box 6)
  - Campaign for state senate 1962 (Box 6)
  - Ionia County Free Fair
    - AMW at fairs (Box 6)
    - Officials undated (Box 6)
    - Flood March 18, 1942 (Box 6)
    - Political officials at fairs (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Ionia County Road Commission
    - Bridge dedication, M-66 December 8, 1948 (Box 6)
    - Road construction
      - circa 1929 (Box 6)
      - 1920s-1930s (Box 6)
    - Site of first roadside picnic table June 11, 1973 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
  - Negatives (Box 6)